This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SE-Radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the IEEE
Computer Society and by IEEE Software
Magazine online at
computer.org/software.
Kolide sends employees important,
timely, and relevant security
recommendations for their Linux, Mac,
and Windows devices right inside Slack.
Kolide is perfect for organizations that
want to move beyond a traditional
lockdown model to one where employees
are educated about security and device
management while they're fixing
important problems.
Visit kolide.com/seradio
to sign up today.
That's k o l i d e dot com slash s e
radio.
Enter your email when prompted to
receive your free Kolide gift bundle
after trial activation.
You can try Kolide with all its features
on an unlimited number of devices for
free for 14 days. No credit card
required.
Try it out at kolide.com/seradio.
For Software Engineering Radio, this is
Robert Blumen.
My guest today is Bruce Momjian.
Bruce is a senior database architect and
Postgres evangelist. He's written widely
on Postgres internals
as a frequent conference speaker on that
subject. He was an adjunct professor at
Drexel University where he taught
database courses and is the author of
Postgres QL introduction and concepts.
Bruce was previously on Software
Engineering Radio number 328
talking about the Postgres query
planner.
And we have done another episode on
Postgres 454
on Postgres as an OLAP database. Bruce,
welcome back to Software Engineering
Radio.
Yeah, it's great to be back. It's been
at least two, maybe three years now.
Yeah.
It's about right. Is there anything
you'd like the audience to know about
you before we get started?
Let's see, I live in Philadelphia.
Obviously, been home for a while because
of COVID, cuz I normally travel quite a
bit, but uh looks like things are
heating up. We have just an event in New
York City last week. We have another
event in Silicon Valley in January, and
we're going to be doing a big conference
in Pasadena
in March. We have one in Russia coming
up, one in Ottawa. We have Percona Live
in Austin. So, there's a lot of cool
stuff going on.
We will be getting to multi-version
concurrency control.
Like to start out briefly describe what
is the Postgres database?
Sure. So, Postgres was originally
designed in 1986
at
University of California, Berkeley by
Michael Stonebraker. He originally
developed Ingres in the 1970s, which one
of one of the early relational systems,
and he developed Postgres 1986 as the
next-generation of relational system.
That's why it's called Postgres or
post-Ingres,
uh technically. What was really
interesting about what he did was he
felt at that time
that extensibility for a database was
critical.
So, the idea of of being able to add new
data types, new indexing methods, new
aggregates, new casts, new stored
procedure languages was going to be part
of his his new database.
What's kind of surprising is that within
the first, probably 20 years after he
did it, haha, that value of
extensibility really was not
appreciated. Even when I started in
1996, that extensibility was kind of a
headache that we had to work through.
But, what's really interesting, if you
look in the past 10, 15 years is that
extendibility that he designed so many
decades ago has allowed Postgres to work
move very seamlessly into data warehouse
tasks, storing JSON, doing full text
search, doing GIS, really kind of making
it available to handle the new data
needs, new data data ingestion that we
have in our for our modern databases.
Cuz back in the '70s, '80s, and '90s,
you know, everyone was at dumb terminals
or PCs and they were sort of typing in
the data. Now we have so much data
coming from,
you know, internet of things and web
apps and mobile apps and telemetry data,
GIS data, that you know, social media
text coming in. So now we've got all
this data ingestion and Postgres because
it was designed to be extendable,
actually is a in a really great position
right now and and that's fueling a lot
of its popularity.
Postgres, like all relational databases,
supports the concept of ACID, that's
ACID transactions. I don't want to
review the entire ACID.
I think Sutter is doing right or even
did an entire episode on this and it was
a very low show number, like three. But
let you just talk about the isolation I
component of the ACID. What does that
mean?
Sure, I'd be glad to. Uh you know, one
of the great things about relational
databases is that it allows you to as an
application programmer to interact with
the database kind of as though you're
the only person
in the database. The best explanation
I've heard is that is that if you're if
you've got static data, static data,
whether it's shared or it's not shared,
is very easy to work with. We can all
think of cases like, you know, a web
server who has static data. Well, that's
easy. You can make multiple copies of it
and just every night update it,
whatever. If you have data that's
volatile and it's private, that's also
very easy to deal with because you only
got one person there. But with with
databases, you basically have volatile
data and it's shared. And the volatile
data and shared, it's very hard to work
with for applications. And application
programmers, when I used to write
applications, when I do a multi-user
app, it was much harder than, you know,
more than twice as hard as a single-user
app.
So, as you said, the ACID capabilities
of of a database make it easy for
programmers to to interact in a in a
simplified manner to the database. And
And what isolation does, the I, is
basically to say that my changes are not
going to be visible until, you know, I'm
not going to see other people's changes
while I'm doing my own work. So, it
gives you sort of a static view of the
data as much as possible,
uh while other people may be changing
the data at the same time.
And obviously, by kind of
allowing the application programmer not
to have to worry about all those ACID
issues, they can write a much cleaner
application and all the complex stuff
gets pushed into the database, where
it's much easier to deal with because
you got all of the shared state
basically be able to share within the
database rather than trying to have the
applications share with each other,
which is almost a disaster.
You know, waiting to happen because it's
just really hard to program in that kind
of environment. So, what isolation does
is to prevent you from seeing other
people's changes while you're doing your
own work.
One way to solve that problem might be
to say we're going to make it appear
that
only one person can use the database at
a time by
locking. And in reality then, only one
person can use the database at the time,
or at least can only modify it.
Talk about locking how locking can
achieve this isolation property and what
are some of the downsides to that?
Sure. So, obviously, if you just have
one giant lock, then then we're going to
prevent anyone from going to the
database while I'm in there and then
when I'm finished, the next person goes
in, that is technically a solution to
handle, you know, the isolation
requirement. The problem with that,
obviously, is the concurrency is
terrible, right? So, what they the first
you know, the the databases from the
'70s, '80s, and and early '90s, their
approach was, "Okay, we can't lock this
whole thing. Can't lock the whole
database for every person. So, we're
going to make the locks granular, right?
So, the early versions, you would lock a
table at a time. So, while I was in the
table,
nobody else could get into the table.
Once I was done with it, then somebody
else could get in. So, you had the sort
of table level granularity. So, you
didn't lock the whole database, you
locked the table you were working with.
Then they got to the point where they
would lock pages. So, you have a table,
it might be a gigabyte in size or at
that point was probably not a gigabyte
in size, it was probably, you know,
maybe a couple megabytes in size, and
you broke it down into pages and you
say, "Okay, I am going to be modifying
this set of pages and I'm going to lock
these and people can do things with
other pages, but these pages I'm I'm not
going to allow somebody into." And then
some of the databases got to row level
locking. So, all of a sudden now, I'm
going to lock the row that I'm looking
at or the row that I'm going to modify,
but then people can do anything with any
of the other rows. But the problem with
that, there's two there's two problems
with that. One, it's a huge amount of
overhead, it's huge amount of locking.
You're really you're really not solving
the concurrency problem, you're
effectively just sort of pushing it into
smaller pieces, right? Uh so, the same
problem we had when we were trying to
lock the whole thing, now we're just we
have the smaller problem, but it's just
at the page level or the table level or
the row level. The second problem, and
this is a was a more insidious problem,
is something called lock escalation.
So the database sometimes didn't know
what your intent was. So you locked a
row, then you locked another row on the
same page, then you locked another row
on the same page, and you started
locking a lot of rows on that page, and
then you're like, the database is like,
"Hmm,
maybe I need to lock this page." So now,
instead of having locks on individual
rows, I need to escalate lock escalation
escalate the lock to that page. Well,
what if somebody else has locked other
rows on that page, and I try and
escalate the lock? It becomes a big
problem. Okay? And sometimes you'd have
to
potentially escalate a page lock to a
table-level lock. Again, same problem.
Do you even have access at that point?
So there was this all In the early '90s
and prior, there was always this problem
called lock escalation, where if you
tried to sort of
it would try and be as granular as
possible, but as your your your job got
bigger and bigger, it started it started
sort of spilling out into other places.
I remember when I used to do database
maintenance in the '90s on Informix, if
I had to do a big update on a table, a
lot of times I would start the update
typically at night, so there was no one
in the database, and I would start at
like 8:00 at night, and then at like
9:15 I'd get an error, and it would say
lock table overflow.
And you'd be like, "Ah,
okay. Now I have to update the first
million rows in a
night, and then and then I got it update
the next million rows, and then I got to
do this until the thing You have to kind
of guess how big the lock table is, so
you don't run another hour 15 minutes
and find out you overflowed it again."
So there was this there was basically
this not only a problem with lock
escalation, but a problem when when of
just just just tracking all these locks
and finding making sure that the lock
table is big enough to do what you
needed to do. And and that gave kind of
database a bad name because people were
like it would it became this mysterious
thing because your application
wanted that isolation responsibility,
but you'd basically
your application would be fine. I didn't
change my application. Why is it failing
all of a sudden with someone else who's
doing something at the same and you'd
have to explain that the application
programmers would be like, well, you
what you do is fine, but then he
something else is running at the same
time and now that affected yours and
maybe you need to run it at night or
another time or go to that other person
tell them not to run that while you're
running this. You can imagine kind of
what a sort of pain that was to to kind
of get going.
You talked about how if all we have is
read
everybody can share it's no problem.
Yeah. It's clear that you have different
people trying to write they can't share.
I believe that if somebody is writing
that they can't share it with readers
because they might not be done updating
the data. Is that correct?
Yeah, that's the problem with the
isolation. So when you only have a
single copy of the row
then as soon as I modify it the old
version is kind of gone. Like you've
overwritten it. It may exist somewhere
in the system, but it's not really in
the table anymore. So if somebody else
comes and they want to read that row
well, we can't show it to them because
of that isolation requirement, right? So
we can't give them the old row either
because we don't know if it's going to
commit or not and so so all of a sudden
that was the other problem that that
even though the example I was giving
previously was two people trying to sort
of write in the same table or the same
pages, the readers were also affected
because you only had one copy and if
that copy was in it was sort of in the
process of being modified, then the
readers would kind of stop and and
they'd block what's going on and that's
often the reason, for example, I had to
do a lot of my work at night cuz I was I
was doing massive updates to to
application tables or you know, and and
anything was massive, you couldn't run
during the day cuz you just you just
knock everybody out because cuz they
would all be like
"Why is the system so slow? I I I did
this half an hour ago and it took 2
seconds and now it's been a minute and
it still isn't done." How do you explain
to somebody? Well, this other person
over there is doing something and they
haven't finished or they started
something and then they went to lunch
and they left they left their terminal
open and you'll have to wait for them to
come back because we can't read that row
at this time. It just it was not it was
not pleasant, no.
So, we've been talking about the need
for
the isolation experience and that you
can solve that with locking, but that
may not be a great solution in a
multi-user system. I think now is a good
time to talk about our main
topic, which is multi-version
concurrency control.
What is it and how does it compare with
locking?
Sure. So, multi-version concurrency
control was originally a paper written
in the late 70s and became popular in
the early 80s as a as a different method
of doing database updates. So, as I said
before, the traditional way, the
space-saving way of of doing updates was
to have one copy of the row.
But, as you can kind of guess from the
word multi-version in multi-version
concurrency control, the way that this
paper decided to solve it was to create
multiple versions of individual rows.
Now, you guys might think kind of like
why would you do that? And how do you
track that, right? You think that would
be just the worst thing in the world
because now you've got you may have a
single row and there might be five
copies in the data in the database and
you'd be like, well, that seems like a
bad idea, right? But, it gets you around
a lot of these problems. So, as I said,
just a look at the most recent example,
the problem of somebody coming to read
data while it's being while somebody
else is writing it. If we do an update
and instead of overriding that row, we
actually create a new version of the row
with the new data and leave the old
version in place, we can have all of the
readers, because they want a consistent,
right? Isolated, consistent version of
the data, they can effectively read the
old version of the row and see a
consistent copy of the database at the
same time that another newer version of
the row is being created, may be
committed, may not be committed, it
depends. But, that gives me the ability
to give sort of what we call consistent
snapshots to all of the users in the
database and to reduce the amount of of
locking, particularly the problem of
readers getting blocked by writers goes
away.
Uh because you always have a copy a you
have one copy of the row that should be
visible to anyone who's currently doing
a read operation in the database.
You use the word snapshot, which I think
from the context I
can guess what you meant, but that turns
out to be a
specific terminology in this domain.
Like you could elaborate on that.
Yeah, that's I mean, that's really a
loaded term, but
the best
it's really a concept. I have to admit I
when I was originally sort of working on
this way back, I you know, I used to
sort of read the code, and then I would
sort of get up from my desk and just
walk around the house for like half an
hour because it took a while
for the idea of what this was doing to
sink in because, you know, we normally
think of of of one, you know, one
object, like a one mug or one set of
glasses or one handkerchief. But, in
this case, you're actually creating
multiple of these.
And
it it's kind of hard to understand
what is going on. But, the reason the
word snapshot is important is that the
snapshot is is a sort of record that's
created when you start your query.
And that snapshot really controls
the acid
particularly the consistency and the
isolation visibility of your of your of
your query. So, once you take that
snapshot at the beginning,
the things that we record in that
snapshot allow us to distinguish which
of the multiple versions of a row should
be visible to you.
Right? So, let's go back to the previous
example. I'm doing an update. Let's
suppose there are five versions of a
row. A row has been updated five times
in the recent history.
That snapshot should tell me which of
those five rows
is visible to my transaction. And only
one of those five should be visible. Or
maybe none of them are visible.
Right? It could be that the snapshot
indicates that none of those rows should
be visible to me, or it might indicate
that the third version or the fifth
version or the second version is the one
that meets a consistent view of the
database for my particular query. So,
that snapshot concept is not is not
unique to Postgres, but it is sort of a
database-y term internals term because
the concept of taking a snapshot is
basically saying
at the time I start my query or
potentially the time I start my
transaction,
this is the time
slot or the the instant that I want to
see the data at. Even if the data's
drifting forward, even if updates are
happening and inserts are happening and
deletes are happening, that snapshot is
going to tie me to a specific consistent
view of the database for the entire
duration of my query.
Although you and I might both using the
database and
in concept we each have our own copy or
snapshot of the entire database, in
reality only need to do a very limited
amount of physical copying to make this
work. Is that right?
Yeah, I mean that would you're right. It
it it would be kind of crazy for us to
make a full copy just to run a query.
So, the way that we do it is that uh
every row has a creation transaction ID
and potentially an expiration
transaction ID. And again, if I look at
the five copies of one row,
each of those five versions of the row
are going to have different transaction
creation and potential expire expiration
IDs on them. And using my snapshot, I
can identify which of those five is
visible to me. So, you're right, we're
only really copying when somebody's
making a change to a row. And we we can
trim off the old versions as soon as
nobody finds those old versions visible.
So, we basically get into a case where
we can either prune away the old
versions if we say, "Okay, we currently
have five versions of that row, but
honestly only versions three to five are
potentially visible to any currently
running transaction.
The version one and version two are so
old that there is no running transaction
that has a snapshot that would ever find
those visible. And if that's true, we
can basically reuse that space right
away.
You brought up now the idea that every
transaction has an ID. How are those IDs
assigned? Are they sequential?
They are sequential. Interesting, we you
know, we've optimized this quite a bit.
So, for example, if a transaction only
is using read-only queries like selects,
it doesn't even get a transaction ID
because it's not going to modify any
data. It doesn't need a transaction ID.
But, any data modification transaction
will get its own transaction ID, and
those are four-byte integers. Obviously,
4 billion, and then once it gets to 4
billion, it'll wrap around to zero
again, and then just go up to 4 billion,
just keeps kind of looping around. And
we have maintenance tasks in the
database which basically handle the the
problem of looping, you know, when it
when it
flips around to zero again, we make sure
that there that all of the old rows are
are proper have proper uh sort of fixed
IDs that will not be interfered with
during the wrap-around.
Going to
mention tendentially, I did research for
this interview from a slide deck that's
on your website. We'll link to that in
the show notes.
You've used the term visibility several
times, and again, I think it's clear
enough in context, but that does turn
out to be another one of those words
that is a term of art within your
domain.
Is there anything you'd like to say
about how you use that word that you
haven't already said?
Yeah, I I love to talk about it. Again,
it's one of those concepts that I start
walking around the house,
kind of scratching my head years ago to
kind of understand what it is.
So,
I think the best way I can explain it is
that if if I'm sitting in a room and my
wife is sitting in the room,
and, you know, we have a
a piece of paper on the on the on the
desk, and I basically tell my wife,
"There's a piece of paper on the desk."
And my wife says, "Yes, I see the piece
of paper."
We have a shared reality. Two of us see
reality the same.
And that works if it's a piece of paper,
right? And we're not writing on it at
the same time, right? But if we start
writing on it at the same time,
then and you and you want both people to
be able to write on the piece of paper
at the same time, things get kind of
complicated. So, if she writes a one,
but she isn't finished yet, and I go
write a two,
should she see my two? And she's by by
asset requirement, she should not see my
two.
So, I see my two, but she doesn't but
and I don't see her one yet, actually.
So, it gets really weird. So, what MVCC
effectively does, in terms of
visibility, is it basically says that
different users in the database
literally see the database differently,
depending on when their query started,
when their snapshot was taken, because
we have to guarantee that they see a
consistent view of the database, even if
the database is changing. So, somebody
who started transaction before me or
after me
is is potentially going to see a
different set of values than I see.
And that's what that's that's why you
don't hear the term visibility used too
much in real the real world, because
there's only one piece of paper on the
desk. My wife can see it, I can see it.
We have one reality, right? We have a
consistent visibility. But but as we
talked about earlier, to handle the high
volume, high concurrency, and high write
volume requirements of
of a database, you actually have to
split apart the concept of visibility.
So, what I see is visible, and what some
other user sees is visible, may be
different.
And And that That's why you don't It's
not a term Yeah, it's a It's a term of
art because it It's almost It's almost
like relativity where somebody's going
very fast and they see the world
differently than somebody standing
still. You're almost kind of in that
scope where where different people who
do things at different times see actual
different realities.
I want to go back into something you
mentioned briefly before.
I start a transaction. I get transaction
ID
100. There are different versions of
some rows that I'm interested in that
have
different snapshot IDs
associated with them. What is the
algorithm for determining which row that
I might read or
write if there's more than one version?
Yeah, it's It's kind of hard to do this
without a diagram. I think the diagram's
in my slides, but effectively,
the verbal way of explaining it is that
when you start a snapshot, when you get
your snapshot at the beginning, the
snapshot should guarantee
that you see all transactions that have
committed before your snapshot.
So, any committed work that happened in
the past
will be visible to you. And And
as a corollary to that, any work that is
in progress and not committed,
or any work that starts after my
snapshot is taken, after my query
starts, those will not be visible to me.
Okay. It's good enough.
There's a slogan that is associated with
MVCC from your slide deck, "Readers
never block writers. Writers never block
readers."
I think at this point it's pretty clear
why that would be the case. If you now
have two transactions and they are both
interested in writing the same rows, do
you have to do something like that lock
escalation procedure that you described
earlier?
So, you're absolutely right that
we say that right reader writers don't
block readers, which is good, right?
Solves the problem we talked about
earlier. Readers don't block writers,
that's also good, right? For if you're
doing a maintenance operation, for
example. But what we don't say,
obviously readers don't block other
readers because that's a non-issue.
But what we don't say is that writers
don't block writers, right? In fact,
writers have to block writers. And the
reason writers have to block writers is
because
when you're updating a row or you're
inserting a row with a unique key that
may already exist, we have to know if
the previous transaction completes or
not. When we do the update or we're
going to insert a duplicate value, we
need to know
is we need to update the most recent
version of this row. So, we talked about
isolation, but in fact, the isolation
kind of goes out the out the window when
you're trying to update another row
because you you effectively have to see
the newest version of that row. We can't
have somebody updating an old version of
that row while somebody is creating a
new version of that row because then you
you get all sorts of weird anomalies.
So, effectively what happens when you
try and update a row that's already
being updated or trying to insert a row
where it has a unique key where another
row has already been inserted but not
committed yet is we basically have to
stop the insert or update until that
transaction either commits or aborts.
And once that transaction commits or
aborts, we then
obviously get a lock on it and then we
can decide if our update or our insert
should continue.
I have this model in mind and it might
not be correct. I'm thinking like Git
where I have master and then I create a
branch.
I do the work on my branch, and at some
point I need to merge I work back into
master.
Is it anything like that, or is it we
have a bunch of these versions and they
all
are still exist, and then the database
has to show you the right version, and
there is no real master?
Yeah, it's more like the latter. When
you're working with Git, you basically
are continually pulling the most recent
sources, and then if there's any
conflict, you have to kind of manually
fix your source code to kind of merge
those in. And then once you do the
commit, then you're going to push
everything up, and you better hope you
have the most recent version, cuz if you
don't, then you make a conflicts on the
push, and then, you know, the whole then
you get another error, right? So, that's
actually one of the things we don't do,
because we don't expect application
programmers to sort of be doing
sort of Git merge like clean up when
something conflicts or whatever. So, we
effectively say, "Okay, I'm going to
update that row, and therefore, if
somebody else has that row locked, I'm
going to wait for them to finish, and
then I'm going to get the most current
I'm going to get a lock myself, so
nobody else can get in. I'm going to get
the current version of that row, I'm
going to process it, and put it back."
So, in Git, the pull and then the the
push, you know, you might go days or
weeks as you're working on your patch,
kind of going through, and you're
continually sort of merging stuff in.
But, in a database, it doesn't really
work that way, because you don't you
don't really want to
you don't want to have two people
committing like on on different versions
of the row, and then somehow have to
merge those two versions together. There
are some database systems that do that,
uh particularly if it's a distributed
database, and they try and sort of have
special data types like add 10 to this
row, but I don't know what the value is,
and they kind of can merge another add
10 together, and it's 20. But there
That's a very specialized use case. In
the relational systems that I know of,
in almost every case, you basically, if
you're going to update the row, you're
going to lock it, and you're going to
wait for that lock to be given to you
exclusively, you're going to perform the
update, and then you're going to send it
back right away.
I've worked with another
feature in an older database. I don't
know if this still exists or is popular.
It was known at the time as optimistic
concurrency control. The way that worked
is if I start a transaction, and it
maybe I don't even know
if I'm going to lock or modify certain
rows in that transaction. The database
will give me some kind of a
version ID,
and then when I commit, I would hand the
version ID back, and if
that row had changed, then my version ID
would be out of date, and the
transaction would fail. So, it's just
fairly simple. Just go back to the
beginning,
just try to do it again, and you'll
refresh at that point. How is that
different than what Postgres does when
you have transactions that I think the
use case is I start out a transaction,
and I might need to modify a row.
Sure. So, we we really have effectively
three different transaction isolation
levels. These are defined by the SQL
standard. The most The The default one,
the most common, is called read
committed. What that effectively means
is that every new statement gets a new
snapshot. So, even if you're in a
multi-statement transaction, every new
query inside that multi-statement
transaction gets a new snapshot. We also
have something called repeatable read,
which means that all of the statements
in a multi-statement transaction get
exactly the same snapshot. So, you take
the snapshot at the beginning of the
transaction, and that snapshot never
changes. And that's really great for
reporting.
So, you know that all your queries in
that transaction are going to see a
consistent view of the database no
matter what's going on, right? So, that
allows you to run financial reports like
in the middle of the day and get an
accurate number cuz in the old days we
could we'd always have to run our
financial reports at night because you
never could get a accurate number during
the day cuz money was moving around, you
know, as you were running the report.
But, we do have a third mode called
serializable, which is much more similar
to the one you're talking about. And in
serializable mode, effectively, it does
exactly that. As you are
running through your multi-statement
transaction, you may read some rows, you
may not do select for update,
right? So, traditionally, people do
select for update, it locks the rows
you've selected, and then you do you
update those rows.
If you
if you want to do optimistic locking,
effectively, just do your select, you
don't do the for update, you go to
modify the rows, and when you do the
commit, it will check to see if if
anything has been modified underneath
you between the time we took the
snapshot and the time you did your
update, and it will throw an error. And
so, serializable mode is been in
Postgres for probably 12 years, I think,
and it and it's really good if you're
doing trying to do exactly what you're
saying, you either aren't able to do
select for updates, you don't want to do
the locking, or maybe
your your application team doesn't
really want to do that, they don't want
to get involved with that, they don't
understand it. And if you're running
serializable mode, effectively, anytime
that something changes between the time
you selected and the time you updated
will be flagged by Postgres, and you'll
get a serializable error, and the
transaction will have to be rerun.
So, we we've been talking about MVCC and
mainly as a solution to the concurrency
problems introduced by
excessive locking or solutions that rely
on locking.
If you are running a report, then you'll
get your own snapshot of the database.
It won't change underneath you while
you're running the report. Even people
who start doing
modifications while the report is
running, you won't see them.
Is that
what users want? Is that Is that
probably a a better solution from I'll
call it a customer standpoint than
something that would give you
a more
frequently updated view of the data
while you're querying it?
Yeah. So, there is a mode that some
databases implement it called dirty
read.
And in dirty read, you basically discard
the ACID requirements. And you basically
say, "I want to see the data as it's
being modified. I don't care if it's not
in my snapshot." Postgres doesn't even
support that mode. And the reason The
reason that you hear people using dirty
read, at least years ago, is that
sometimes that was the only way you
could get work done, right? If you had a
non-MVCC
database,
you know, you'd be kind of like, "Um I
This number might be wrong that I'm
computing, but it's never going to
finish if I don't use dirty read. So,
I'm just going to run it and I'm going
to have a lot of caveats about whether
this number is accurate or not."
What Databases that use MVCC, like
Postgres, they really don't need dirty
read because they don't have the problem
of writers blocking readers anymore.
So, Postgres does not support that mode.
I don't know if anybody's actually asked
for that mode because effectively that
would mean that not I'm not talking
about the snapshot changing between
queries. That's the default for
Postgres. But, if you want the
visibility to change as the query's
running and somebody, you know, you're
on page 10, somebody adds something to
page 11, and you see it right away, even
though they haven't even, you know,
that row wasn't even there when you
started your scan. Most people don't
want that because it's hard to really
rely on the data, whereas with an MVCC
system, because you have the writers not
blocking readers, you get an accurate
number. The number may be
old, it may only be accurate to the time
you started your your query, but it is
accurate as of that time.
And there are very few people who really
want to see dirty data that effectively
does not give them an accurate number of
anything because they could be moving
$100 from one account to the other. You
may see that $100 leave on page 11, and
you may you realize that it appears on
page four, but you've already read page
four, so you don't see it. And that's
the classic case where the number may be
a little more
current in terms of what it sees, but
because it isn't consistent, it isn't
really accurate anymore.
I know a lot of reporting would be
things from the past. For example, on
the 1st of the month, we want to run a
financial report for the previous month.
So, you're really only dealing with the
data that can't change at that point
anyway, and
it's definitely better that your query
will reliably complete in a short time
than
caring about transactions that occurred
after the first, which aren't even part
of your query anyway.
Yeah, well, the the problem is not
I don't think people would be upset if
we consistently showed
changes from queries that happened after
we started.
What they don't want is to see pieces
of of query of of changes that happened.
And that's where the A atomicity comes
from. So, the problem is that you might
see the delete that happened, but the
insert might be earlier in the table and
you might have passed that already. So,
imagine somebody scanning through a
table, they're adding $100 to one
account, deleting $100 from another
account. The addition may be forward in
the table for you, so you would see it,
but the deletion may be behind you in
the table, so you wouldn't see it. And
that's really the problem. There's
really no way
in that I could think of, frankly, that
we would show somebody a a full
completed transaction that had happened
while the session was running, because
you have to realize it's not just one
table. It could be we could be touching
multiple tables, we could be doing a
join, there could be index entries
involved, right? So, there's all this
stuff going on, and the idea that we
would say, "Oh, oh, okay, that was an
insert that happened, and there's no
delete with it, and maybe that's okay."
So, I'll just throw that into the total,
right? You just don't know, because you
don't know the SQL language really
doesn't give you the ability to say,
"I'm just doing an insert. If you want
to show it to people before I commit, go
ahead. I don't have a delete associated
with this. It's only an insert." But
then, all There's all these things
happening in the indexes and page splits
and it's just really hard to understand
how that would work effectively.
You mentioned that Postgres was designed
from the beginning to be extensible, so
you can add new data types.
For someone adding a new data type, are
there
operations or methods they need to write
in order for it to work properly with
MVCC?
Actually, no. The
Yeah, it's it's kind of funny. A lot of
databases seeing Postgres' popularity, a
lot of databases kind of got into the
extensible, you know, bandwagon. But,
you know, it's really hard to do because
Postgres was designed originally with
this,
we've been able to do it, but it's
really hard to sort of retrofit it into
a system. So, because Postgres was
designed to the beginning for this, it
has
all these system tables which store all
the data types, the ones that are
built-in and the extendable ones, the
ones you add. It has all the indexing
stuff is stored in system tables. All of
the stored procedure language
definitions are stored in All the
aggregates are stored in system tables.
So, effectively, the API for how all of
this stuff is handled, when you're
creating a new data type, you really
have to worry about, you know, define
how long it's going to be or variable
length. You have to define an input
function, and you have to define an
output function, right? That's pretty
much it.
Now, you probably want some other
functions to work on the data. You might
want, you know, some casting functions
to get your data in and out different
data types, but it's actually really
easy to do. You don't have to muck with
all that other stuff. You just need to
tell us how the data is going to come
in, and Postgres, because it was
designed this way, just kind of fits it
into rows, automatically puts the
transaction IDs on the front, and
there's really no special handling for
any data type related to MVCC all at all
that I can think of.
In the enterprise database landscape, do
most or all the vendors support MVCC?
Oracle does. They've had, I think,
since the late '90s. I believe
Microsoft has it as an option, but last
I looked, it was not enabled by default.
I don't know about DB2. I think they
also have it available but not on as a
default. I think there are some others.
I want to say
Cassandra uses something similar.
There's some of the no sequel databases
use it a little bit. I think I don't
remember if my sequel Maria DB I think
they might use it. I don't know.
Postgres's implementation is a little
unusual because we just leave the old
rows in place and we put new rows in. A
lot of systems like Oracle don't
technically do that. They actually take
the old row and they put it into like a
an undo segment. And they actually have
like pointers and when you go through
the table, that maybe isn't the row you
want. You sort of jump over somewhere
else to kind of pull the undo pull the
right version and so forth. But Postgres
just kind of leaves it in the table,
which is sort of a unique approach to to
handling the MVCC problem. But getting
back to actually what I just talked
about, it has been difficult for
traditional relational systems to add
MVCC. I know that Microsoft tried it. I
know DB2 has has done some stuff with it
as well. But the problem was that a lot
of the applications written particularly
for Microsoft SQL
are so used to the
the the locking behavior that they had
trouble
making a true MVCC system that would
also work properly and perform it with
the
applications they currently were
deployed on it.
Did Postgres run into that problem or
any other interesting challenges when
this was added to Postgres?
No, we did I think in 2000 2001. Vadim
Mikheev was the guy who sort of added
it. At that time we already had sort of
the vestiges of of an MVCC system when
it when the original design of Postgres
was to allow for time travel so you
would allow or you could you could run a
query and get the results as of like
last week.
And there was a concept that there were
going to be these worm drives,
write-only, read-many worm drives that
that would keep the old versions and
you'd keep maybe, you know, a year's
worth or 10 years worth of old versions
and you you had like these CDs, these
worm drives which would, I guess, allow
you to access old versions of the row.
So, the concept of having multiple
versions was kind of built into
Postgres. What we didn't have was the
MVCC capability. But, when it was added
in 2000 2001, 90 99, I mean, we our our
community was so small that, you know,
everyone was like, "Great. Whatever you
Whatever you think is good, Vadim, you
go at it." And, you know, it's it's
served us well. It is complicated. The
cleanup of the rows can be challenging,
particularly in very high write volume
systems. But, it behaves really well.
And when you benchmark it against Oracle
or other systems, it actually behaves
better in a lot of ways. Partially
because
the way because the old row stays in
place and the new row gets added right
next to it typically, you don't have
this sort of bottleneck in an undo
segment where there's this huge
concurrency of people all trying to find
the right version of the row. We just
kind of leave
It's like we just like leave them strewn
across the floor and then later we come
off and we clean them up. But, it turned
out to be a pretty nice clean design for
us and one that doesn't have a lot of
downsides in terms of performance.
You just introduced the topic of
cleanup. I'm aware from
your slide deck that the system does do
some cleanup.
I could see that if you have a lot of
writes going on, you end up with a lot
of old rows that are no longer
current for any query.
How does the cleanup process work?
Yeah, there there's really two scopes to
the clean up. One is what I call
pruning.
And this can happen at any time. It's a
very lightweight operation. Even a
select practically can cause pruning.
All pruning does is to remove old
versions of the row. It looks at it as
you're doing a sequential scan. Let's
say for a select, you read the page, you
read all the rows on the page. You're
you're seeing the transaction IDs. And
you can look, okay, this was expired by
transaction 100. All the snapshots
currently don't can't see anything older
than that. So, nobody can see that row.
That's what we referenced earlier. Some
rows are very quick to identify. This
row cannot be seen by any running
transactions. And the system will just
will just restructure the page and free
up that space right away even as during
the select. Postgres 14 added that
capability to indexes. So, if you're
spinning through an index in Postgres 14
and you're about to split the page, then
B-tree pages are split. It's fairly
expensive, very hard to undo a split.
And one of our, you know, Peter
Geoghegan
was able to identify that we're getting
a lot of splits in cases where we really
don't need to split because there's a
lot of dead rows on in the index. So, in
Postgres 14, he along with somebody from
Russia kind of worked together on on
kind of getting this this
sort of what we call index pruning
working. And I think that's going to
have, you know, great benefits to
Postgres.
But there are cases that don't work that
way. And we have a autovacuum process
that runs continually, wakes up every
minute, looks to see what tables
potentially have a lot of dead rows in
it, what indexes need to be cleaned up.
And it just kind of runs in the
background freeing up that space and
making it available. The nice thing for
us is that that autovacuum process is
not done in the foreground. It's not
something that that a query is normally
going to be working with. It's basically
just kind of running at a low priority
in the background kind of just doing
regular cleanup. And we would need that
anyway, even if we didn't use MVCC and
we used the old version, you still have
when you when you abort a transaction,
you still need to clean up the old
aborted rows. So, even if we did MVCC
differently, we would still have Imagine
you do an insert of 1,000 rows and you
get 900 of them in and your transaction
aborts. Well, with somebody's got to get
rid of those 900 rows.
So, fortunately, we have an auto vacuum
process that handles that and handles
the the issue of having multiple
versions of an updated row at the same
time and deleted rows, of course. They
need to be cleaned up, too.
This sounds a lot like how garbage
collection works in programming
languages. Is that a good comparison?
It it is. It is. You know, there there's
some languages like C where you
basically allocate everything and you
free everything manually, right? Which
is what Postgres is written in, so I'm
I'm obviously very familiar with that
method. And then you have more of the
Pearl style
where the language counts the number of
references.
And when the number of references drops
to zero, it automatically frees that
memory. So, it kind of identifies, it
tracks where the variable is, it is in
its scope, has somebody sent a pointer
to that somewhere else? And then as soon
as it isn't in scope anymore, the the
memory's freed. And in the Java case, of
course, you basically have We just
allocate stuff on the fly and then
occasionally a garbage collector comes
along and starts to run and just sort of
looks through all the objects. There's
not the reference counting in the same
way. It just kind of looks at all the
objects and saying which ones are
visible, which ones have been thrown
away, and just kind of cleans them up.
And yeah, Postgres is much more in that
style of design. Oracle, I would say is
more in the Pearl style where they
they're more They're They've You've this
undo segment where all the old rows go
to, and I believe they kind of m- manage
the references to that a little
differently than than we do.
In your slides, there's a term I came
across in this section, storage space
reuse.
Is that anything different than what
we've already talked about?
So,
yeah, it is. Well,
you know,
so when I'm when I'm talking about page
pruning and the auto vacuum, what
they're effectively doing is they're
taking data that they know is is no
longer useful, and they're basically
freeing it up. So, a page that used to
be 90% full, now it's 20% full, cuz we
freed up 70% that was just dead, right?
And if the pages at the end of the table
or all empty, we can truncate the table
down, right? So, if you if you delete
all the rows in the table, then vacuum
will effectively shrink the file to
zero, because it knows there's a whole
bunch of empty rows at the end. In fact,
the whole thing is empty, and it'll just
shrink it down to zero.
But,
and the same thing with indexes, we'll
we'll we'll reduce the size of the page.
Maybe, you know, if if we're about to
split a page and we determine there's a
lot of dead rows on there, we'll cut it
down, you know, so now now maybe it's
40% full instead of being 90% full.
What we typically don't do is to free up
all potential space to the operating
system.
So, for example, if you have a table and
you deleted every other row in the
table,
okay? And it's interspersed. So, every
page is now 50% full, right? That 50%
that remaining empty 50% is ready for
the next insert or the next update,
right? But, what we won't do
automatically is to basically shrink
down that table,
because it potentially the table could
be half the size.
Right? Because each page is 50%, so if
we got all the empty space together, it
would all it would be half the table and
then we'd have 50
you know, half the size all full pages.
We have a manual command called vacuum
full that does that which would
basically
compress the table down and return all
that space to the operating system.
But but that's not something we can do
automatically because it locks the
table.
And obviously people can't do that in
production. So if you're doing a lot of
big maintenance operations
and you you've you've removed a lot of
data from the table or or maybe from an
index and
you basically like I'm probably never
going to need that space again. Like I'm
I'm not going to be adding new rows or
that that that that empty space in the
page is probably not going to be useful
to me, then you might want to run vacuum
full. And pretty much all the databases
have this problem. You can't really be
shrinking down stuff while people are in
the database. You can't unsplit a B-tree
page very easily.
So effectively the only way to do it is
to lock it, create a new copy, and then
delete the old copy. We also have a
reindex command which does that for
indexes. So if you want to just rebuild
an index, you can do the reindex. If you
want to do the index and the table
itself, your your vacuum full would be
the way to do that. Or cluster which
also pretty much does the same thing.
But you get to the limitations of
concurrency that there's certain
operations that are just so
potentially
disruptive to normal workloads that you
have to push them as utility commands,
and if you want to run them, you have to
make sure you do it at a quiet at a time
when there are very few people using the
database.
From our discussion, I understand this
is a feature which is intended to give
developers or SQL query programmers a
good intuitive experience
and good database performance without
them having to really think about it a
lot. But, is there anything that SQL
developers do need to know in order to
get the most out of MVCC?
I you know
I don't think so. I mean
it it
we we when we had that we used to do the
locking
Yeah, uh when we had non-MVCC systems,
application programmers either they
either they needed to know about it or
they soon learned they needed to know
about it because their applications
would not run right and somebody would
come to them and they would say
"Why did you write this code this way?"
And the person would say, "Well, because
XYZ." And they they'll basically that
would never that is never going to work
in our system. We have to do it this
other way. With MVCC
I don't think there's anything that
really an application programmer needs
to know needs to do differently.
I I think there are certain maintenance
operations. Again, if you're deleting
80% of a table and you're never going to
use the rest of the space, you might
want to do a vacuum full on that. But,
other than that, really not. It it's
it's really very transparent. I think
the only the only real caveat is is the
the issue you brought up earlier. Either
you need to do a if you're going to do
select
and then you're going to update the rows
in the same transaction and you're going
to rely on synchronization between the
data you get out of the select and the
updates you do, you either have to run
select for update or you have to run in
serializable mode and be willing to
retry when you get a transaction error
on commit. Those are not specific to
MVCC, but they are, you know, generally
good practice in any concurrency system.
Bruce, I I we've covered some really
good subtopics within this area. Is
there anything
that you want to add that we haven't
talked about?
I probably probably the only thing and I
did a talk last night for Asia and I
brought up this topic, but there's this
thing called right amplification
that we still I think struggle with in
Postgres and that is because of the way
we do MVCC, say
Postgres has a tendency to to issue
somewhat more rights than other
relational systems.
Part of it's because of the way we do
MVCC because we have the old and new
versions in the same
page hopefully in the same table and we
just sort of age them out as you said
with the garbage collection. So, when
that garbage collection happens, even
though it's happening in the background,
it is issuing rights to the to the to
the storage.
When the transaction
when when we are updating the hint bits
of the the hint bits or the basically
the bits that tell us, you know, which
transactions are committed or aborted,
we're going to issue rights potentially
for those. Again, these are all
background rights, they're not happening
in the foreground of the of the
application, but they are rights and
they are increasing the right volume.
And as I said before, when when the
transaction ID counter wraps around, we
have to make sure that none of the old
rows have transaction IDs that would now
be duplicated. So, we have to issue a
freeze operation. So, there's a sense
that we have a number of
ways we do things that are a little more
right heavy
than other databases. That's not a
problem for most people, but it is a
problem for some people.
And we continue to make incremental
improvements on this. As I said in
Postgres 13, we improved the way we
handle duplicates in indexes. In
Postgres 14, we improved the way that we
do index cleanups, uh index pruning
basically, on the fly to produce the
number of page splits, which will
greatly reduce the need for re-index.
But, we keep chipping away at it and and
it's just something that
you know, if you look back at Postgres
like 9.2, 9.3, and you look at the right
profile there, and you look at the
profile of the same Postgres 13 or 14,
you're going to see a much reduced right
profile, but it's still there.
And I don't know if there's a great way
to solve that without adding a whole lot
of other negatives to the system. So, we
have a lot of smart people looking at
it. Obviously, we're a very open
project, and people are giving opinions
all the time. I don't know if we need to
do something drastic here, like a new
way of doing things, or if our
incremental approaches is acceptable.
Currently, it seems to be acceptable
almost everyone, and we continue to make
small improvements every year, but it is
something you should be aware of that
that that this MVCC does not come
without cost. There is a cost in terms
of having to have the the two
transaction IDs on every row, on having
to update the hint bits, on having to
handle the cleanup in the background,
and then having to do the freezing.
These are, you know, right operations
that do happen.
Thank you for that. Before we wrap up,
would you like to point listeners
anywhere that they can find you or any
projects you're involved with on the
internet?
Sure. My website momjian.us has 57
talks,
93,
94 videos, and over 600 blog entries.
So,
I've got a lot of stuff there. I just
sort of modernized the web page a little
bit to be a little fresher. Of course,
the postgres.org website has a huge
amount of information about Postgres,
and there's even a website called PG
Life, which I maintain, which gives you
a snapshot of what's happening in now in
the community. And if you're curious
about what's going on, you can find a
link to that on my post grace blog
webpage.
Bruce, thank you so much for speaking to
software engineering radio.
My pleasure.
For Software Engineering Radio, this has
been Robert Blumen. Thank you for
listening.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE Software Magazine. For more about
the podcast, including other episodes,
visit our website at SE-Radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website, or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
SE-Radio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
team@se-radio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
License 2.5.
Thanks for listening.